[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer
door / software so welcome to a new
episode of se radio today I'm talking to
J fields about the topic of unit testing
actually working effectively with the
unit tests so J welcome to the show and
why don't you start off by introducing
yourself yeah great thank you very much
for having me J fields I work for deer
to be trading and before that I worked
for thought works so I have a bit of
experience with consulting and a bit of
experience working full time and you
know I think those are both great
environments and I'm glad I've gotten to
work in both and that's given me
exposure to various ways to unit tests
and hopefully I've found something that
can make other people productive as well
so my assumption would be that probably
a 100% of our listeners know what unit
tests are and I using them but I may be
wrong and even if I'm not I'd still like
you to explain to us what human test
actually is and how it differs from
other kinds of tests yeah absolutely
unit test is a it's a very tricky term
in my opinion if you asked a hundred
people I'm not sure you'd get the same
answer from anyone and recently I was
was really trying to influence the
community to make a more strict
definition of unit test and Martin
Fowler basically convinced me that that
was a terrible idea because I'm never
gonna be able to convince the community
to come up with anything more strict if
you go to Wikipedia you can see that the
definition on Wikipedia is in computer
programming unit testing is a software
testing method by which individual units
of source code sets of one or more
computer program modules together with
associated control data usage procedures
and operating procedures are tested to
determine whether or not they're fit for
use so it's not a great definition in my
opinion because it's basically saying in
so units could be methods or functions
but then it says modules which could be
you know entire components of an
application procedures operating
procedures usage procedures it's just
very general and I think it almost
reduces to tests I mean there's there's
not much specific about it mmm-hmm so so
what do you see as the critical or as
the best size of one of those units when
would you when do you think it's
justified to call something a unit test
as opposed depends on the language
obviously but my experience has been in
rubies he sharp Java
Clojure and in the object-oriented
languages I prefer to test at the method
level so maybe one test fixture so one
class one click one test class for every
class in the application and then one
too many tests for every method that
needs to be tested and then in
functional languages probably one test
namespace for every domain name space
and one too many tests for every
function that deserves to be tested so
the original article on the topic was
called test infected programmers loved
writing tests do you think that's true
do programmers love writing tests and if
they don't what's it what's a good way
to get them to love tests I think the
first time you start writing tests you
fall in love with a couple things you
know assuming tester for you I think you
fall in love with the fact that you can
kind of play around in there and you
know that there's unlikely to be impact
in production code so you can experiment
a little in your tests and I don't know
many programmers that don't love
experimenting and I also think they fall
in love with the confidence that you can
gain from writing tests so it's very
easy to fall in love with code where you
can be playful and then tell yourself
that you know there's also value to this
code it's giving me confidence in my
application for people who don't
necessarily love it I think
they would maybe fall into two
categories people who simply believe
they don't have enough time to write
tests and I think that's just a terrible
justification I mean if you don't have
time to write tests it's you know
possibly because you're always debugging
and maybe you wouldn't have to debug so
often if you were writing tests or it
may also be people that have worked with
tests that haven't provided them as much
value as they'd expected and for those
people I would encourage them to not
necessarily dive back in but maybe see
if there's another way that they could
write tests that would provide them more
value in the future and maybe they'll
they'll fall back in love with writing
tests what do you say it's a fair it's a
fair characterization to say that you
know test is is is the test that you
mostly write for yourself that you have
the most motivation to write to gain
personal benefits from it is that a fair
characterization I think that's what
most people do absolutely especially
people who are in love with unit testing
I think that most people approach to
unit testing from the frame of mind of
what's best for me right now in creating
creating some new code creating a new
feature for the first time and what's
best for me when I want to maintain it
and I would say that's actually not
necessarily great I think in general you
probably want to put the team first and
maybe if you put the team first and the
team put the team first maybe you
wouldn't run into so many tests that are
painful to work with so from a
programmers perspective I think unit
tests are the easiest form of test or at
least they seem very easy given that
that is the case or that most people
think that's the case why did you end up
writing a book on the topic and in fact
while we're recording this episode sure
I think that unit tests are very
approachable they're very easy to write
and they're even easier maybe to write
poorly and it's funny when I first
started writing this book I contacted
Martin Fowler and just said hey I'm
think about writing this book and I have
three chapters maybe you know if you
have some free time you can take a look
and he replied right away and said I
don't know why you're writing about that
the space really seems pretty mined out
where his exact words and it really put
me off
I respect Martin quite a bit and I
thought man if he
thinks this is a bad endeavor than
probably I should probably give up right
away to be honest
luckily for me a couple other people
said I think that what you have is
pretty good and I think you should keep
going and eventually I don't even know
what happened but you know Martin had
access to the book the whole time as I
was writing it and one day he said hey I
heard you finished and so I'm gonna give
the book a read and a couple days later
he said this is really really good and I
hope that you get the word out you know
I hope people you I hope people read
this book and the thing that hopefully
other people find valuable that I think
he thinks is valuable about the book is
that it gives unit testing it gives you
a view in the unit testing from
someone's point of view it gives you
what I think is practical a practical
way to approach unit testing and I don't
think you see a lot of that out there I
think they're really good beginner books
and they're books that give you a lot of
different detail for example the X unit
books give you a lot of detail on you
know pretty much everything that you
could possibly think of I don't I don't
remember how long that book is I know
that I never got through it cover to
cover but I think it's maybe 700 pages
long fantastic reference manual and then
another book that I got through recently
was the art of unit testing and again I
think it's a great book but it's an
intro book so I think there's a void
there there's a space for more people to
write about not just you know the hello
world of unit testing writing that first
test and setting up the framework
there's a big gap between that and then
the reference material this is here the
patterns for unit testing I think that
the community as a whole could benefit
from a couple books where people say
here's how I like to write my unit tests
here's the guidance in kind of the big
picture way you know a blog post here
and there about unit testing is great
but we have 10 years of blog posts from
from very talented people but no
comprehensive view into how these people
work effectively so that's that's really
what I set out to do in the book was
take a lot of the experience that I've
picked up over the last dozen years
and put it together in a way that shows
more than the trivial blog post example
it takes a domain that people are
familiar with and takes some tests that
look about as terrible as you would
expect if you're a consultant or a
full-time employee that picks up
somebody else's codebase and evolves the
tests in very concrete ways showing you
know basically every line evolves them
to what I believe is a more maintainable
style of unit testing so so what is what
is it an example of what are some
examples of things that people do wrong
when they write unit tests I think
mostly all of it stems from thinking
about yourself thinking about what's
going to make you successful right now a
lot of people conflate test-driven
development and unit testing is if
they're the same thing but they're not
you know and a test that you wrote to
help you create a feature a test that
you use to to TDD a new feature for your
application that test is not guaranteed
to be valuable for you in the long term
so just because the test helped you
write the feature there are a lot of
things you can do from there that I
don't think people do you can first of
all just delete the test if you just
wrote a test because you weren't really
sure how you wanted things to work and
you now have a working feature and that
feature is you know nice to have maybe
one user wants to use this feature every
three months and if things go wrong
nobody cares you get a phone call and
maybe you update a database table
yourself or something trivial like that
do you really want to strap yourself
with additional code that you have to
maintain over time I mean it's more
likely that that feature will change to
be maybe more valuable or maybe go away
than it is that a bug will creep in and
that test will save you and you know
like I said if you look at the test
anything what's what's the return on
investment for this test ROI is
something I like to use a lot when I
talk about tests so if this test is
gonna save me from getting a phone call
once every six months maybe then maybe I
don't want to maintain it in my codebase
so the first thing that I think you have
to do is look at your test and determine
okay it helps me TDD fantastic but does
it still need to be here and if the
answer's no then you need to delete it
if you think that it did help you and
you think that it is important you know
let's say you're reading an insurance
application that needs to look up
customers by you know you're in the u.s.
so social security number and you know
this seems like a pretty important
feature being able to look up your
customers so you wrote a test that
helped you TDD it but that doesn't mean
that that's the best test that's gonna
help you maintain that code so look at
the code again you know maybe if it's
really critical to your application grab
somebody else and say you know if this
test were failing right now what clues
would you want in order to figure out
the source of the problem as fast as
possible and change a test to go from
helping you deliver a feature to helping
you maintain value in the system so the
very first difference seems to be that
if you do test-driven development if you
see if you use tests to just create the
code in the first place it might that
might mean that you have something
different than what is useful in the
long run so assuming that you create
something that you want to be valuable
in the long run what are some things
that you have to think about what makes
a test good and maintainable under that
circumstances I would say
approachability
is key to start with so whenever I
whenever I see your test failing you
know a test that you may have written
six months ago and you've long since
moved on and I've never seen it before
what kind of clues does the test give me
does it tell me where I can look in the
domain to figure out what's going on I
think another thing that bothers
maintain errs in general is how much
test code do you have to wade through
before you can figure out what's
actually wrong if you have say a test
that someone has used dry to kind of
make you know most people apply dry in a
way that that insures that the least
number of characters are used but that's
not necessarily the best way to write a
test you're talking about dryers and
don't repeat yourself right yes exactly
you know that if you come to a test for
a first time and it's failing and you
know more than likely when a test is
failing and it surprises you it's
because it seems unrelated to what
you're doing
so you're annoyed because you you want
to move on you're in the middle of
delivering some feature and you see
something that looks like it's unrelated
and so you're annoyed as to
why it's breaking so if you open it and
you can pretty quickly figure out what's
going on by just looking at the broken
method the test method then you're
probably not too annoyed and you just
move on but if you open it and there's
some variable in there some field level
variable in a java class I guess and
it's initialized you know maybe it's
declared at the top and then it's
initialized somewhere but you don't
really know where so now you have to
find usages so maybe you find a setup
method or maybe you find a helper method
or something like that you start
navigating around and you're just moving
farther and farther away from what you
wanted to do which was just deliver a
feature that seems somewhat unrelated so
I think not necessarily well
specifically I think repeating yourself
in ways that will enable someone that's
never seen the test before to more
quickly understand what's going on can
be a good thing you know when you're
looking at a test suite as a whole if
there are ways that you can get rid of
duplication for example running all of
your database updates in a transaction
and then rolling everything back is
obviously just a good idea
well when compared with trying to do
that in every single test individually
so that's great
apply apply some type of dry to the test
suite level and then within a test
obviously you probably don't want to
repeat too many things but when it comes
to a grouping of tests for maintainer x'
maybe the best thing is actually not
knowing that there's a grouping of tests
I mean when's the last time you saw a
grouping of tests and they all failed
together when they all fail together
then you look at all the infrastructure
code and it's valuable because it all
makes sense in the grouping but when two
out of five fail and you need to
understand all of the logic built into
the grouping then you've spent some
decent time understanding that logic and
that was helpful too - but every second
that you spent trying to understand the
infrastructure that applies to the other
three that are still passing is
basically waste so avoiding reducing the
code or the characters specifically as
much as possible I think is a great way
to create more maintainable tests again
just considering what the value of the
test is you know it
at first it's for creating but after
that it becomes about maintaining I
think you also want to avoid pretty much
any type of looping constructs or
reflection if possible basically what
you want are straightforward tests that
you can easily navigate and only when
necessary and only navigate into domain
code if possible mm-hmm
so they seem to be different rules for
the test code is for the rest of the
system do you consider it a necessity
that the test code is as maintainable is
the production code or more or less what
is what's your feeling there sure when
when I was first started when I first
started consulting at ThoughtWorks
I used to i don't know i din errs talk
to some of the other team members and i
would ask them the silly question of
which would you rather have a perfect
test suite or a perfect codebase and you
know inevitably they were pragmatic and
said a perfect codebase and I would
always say that makes no sense because a
perfect test suite would guarantee that
the codebase was perfect which is which
is really not true I mean if the tests
we were perfect then it wouldn't have
tests that must be maintained for
features with small return on investment
so you can't guarantee that the codebase
is going to be perfect if the tests are
perfect so the first thing I would say
is it really makes no sense even from a
high level to approach the two pieces of
code in the same way one is one should
be the tests specifically should be
approached from value in my opinion
what's the value of the test with
respect to keeping the application up
whereas you know in production obviously
pretty much all code should be created
pretty equally
I mean in a bug in some trivial feature
can just as easily take down the system
with an exception I would assume mm-hm
so yeah you you want to apply different
thinking to your tests and you want to
also you really want to approach the
tests in a way where perhaps readability
is more important than performance but
at the same time performance is still
going to be important enough on a
different scale you know I work in the
trading industry and often
milliseconds are important to us and
when you're looking at tests you know
individual milliseconds for tests
probably not a big deal but when the
test suite starts to run at around 10
minutes or something ridiculous like
that then you have to wonder if people
are even gonna keep using the test suite
so there are a lot of trade-offs but I
think you start with readability because
you want people to be able to maintain
your tests and then you start making
trade-offs where necessary yeah how much
is this related to the debate that
recently was going on between I think
Kent Beck and Martin Fowler and David
Hyneman Hansen aroud unit tests are a
waste of time I think that was the
original original statement made by DHH
by David Hyneman hasn't the creator of
Ruby on Rails what's your what's your
take on this whole thing did you follow
it and what do you have an opinion on it
I did follow it and I would agree it
sounds like his tests are a waste of
time no you know you're gonna get what
you put into it and I think that it's
very like I said before it's very easy
to write terrible tests and it's very
easy to then blame the tests and to be
honest I would advise every single
person out there who's writing tests
that are not making them more productive
to just stop I mean if they're not
making you more productive you shouldn't
do it
you can replace tests there with any
activity any activity that's not making
you more productive seems like a
no-brainer to stop I mean you know given
no other motivation so I think when you
get to that situation you really have a
choice to make
do you want to continue - well obviously
you should just stop writing tests that
aren't making you more productive and so
I'm sure their tests were waste and I
hope that they did delete them and thus
they're dead but that doesn't mean that
everybody is is spending time that they
shouldn't on testing I think there's
plenty of unit tests out there that are
very helpful I mean my my team is
working on several code bases that are
several years old and I think the
longest-running test suite is ten
seconds and that includes going to the
file system database you know whatever
crossing boundaries we have to do and we
find all types of issue
with our unit tests and they make us
more productive but you know like I've
been harping on we also keep an eye out
for tests that make us less productive
and we delete those tests quickly so I
actually applaud thh for coming out and
kind of saying this this sacred cow is
not necessarily what it's made out to be
and I think more people should delete
their tests if they're not finding them
helpful but then they have a choice to
make do you want to just go without
tests do you want to go without that
confidence you know because it wasn't
all bad you didn't start out with a test
suite where it was all bad at some point
it was probably providing you value so
do you want to invest in trying to write
better unit tests I mean that'll be up
to the individual but it seems to me
like it's something worth investing in
but unless they found some other way to
get confidence in building systems but
yeah I don't know I haven't seen a lot
of that out there mm-hmm so I had
originally planned to ask you whether
there is such a thing as having too many
tests but I think you've just answered
it right there are too many tests if if
there's stupid tests if they don't bring
value then you shouldn't have that yeah
I think too many tests is the same as
not enough tests in both cases it's
suboptimal you you don't whether you
waste time debugging because you don't
have enough tests or you waste time
maintaining tests that don't need to be
there at the end of the day both of
those things amount to waste
mm-hmm what do you think about a metric
like code coverage is that a useful
thing I do think code coverage is a
useful thing I remember when relevance
was now cognate echt was putting on a
pretend code coverage in their contracts
and I thought it was pretty cool I
thought it was a great idea but they
don't do that anymore and most people I
know aren't looking for a hundred
percent code coverage because you have
to do silly things for example it's been
grabbed exactly that's exactly what I
was going to say also testing framework
methods you know but I personally don't
have any desire to test joda-time
ever again you know I'm gonna go ahead
and expect joda-time works and I want to
use it without having to fight some
silly test coverage battle mmm makes
perfect sense so okay let's let's talk a
bit about some of the different ways or
some of it maybe some of the different
aspects that one might want to test so
what are some different things that you
might want to test for and how would you
go about it you know for me it's always
just the the most complex parts of the
system that provide the most value
that's all I really look at so I I spoke
before about the insurance company and
an insurance company that relies on a
social security number in order to find
their customers so we're all writing
that system I would probably have a lot
of tests around trying to ensure that
the social security numbers were valid
and I would you know we want to build
these people so I would have tests
around credit card validation and I
would have tests around billing
addresses and then I would I would shy
away from tests such as ensuring that
their name is alphanumeric because
number one people seem to be using
numbers now and in the past I imagine we
would have tests that that checked for
that and now you have to switch those
tests alphanumeric but at the end of the
day does it really matter I mean as long
as the billing is going through and if
the customer really gets upset about
having their name misspelled then they
call you and it's some call center
person that that updates the name it's
not really a big deal you know so that's
that's what I look at from from
determining how important a test is if
the if the system needs needs a specific
feature in order to work then it needs
to be tested and all corner cases likely
need to be tested that needs to be the
robust part if the system can continue
functioning without you know much impact
or with no impact then I would say those
are the tests that have less value and
those are the tests that I would look to
not have mm-hmm you mentioned in passing
that your ten second test Suites hit the
file system and hit the database
I've heard people express the opinion
that this doesn't even qualify as a unit
test if it does something like that
what's retake on that yeah the first
version of the book that I wrote that
was exactly how I defined it I said that
unit tests were not allowed to cross
boundaries so no messaging no file
system no database
and they also would only specify
concrete classes for the class under
test and like I said Martin Fowler got
ahold of me and said this is not it's
not gonna work you're not gonna convince
the industry that this is had a unit
test there's just too much momentum from
people who believe that unit testing is
allowed to hit the database and he
convinced me that it that it was a bad
plan to try to redefine it and I've come
to terms with the fact that unit testing
is just such a general term that you
just have to roll with that and then you
have to there are other terms that can
allow you to express your ideas so you
can you can have tests whether you want
to call them unit tests or not you gonna
have tests that don't hit the database
that don't hit the file system test that
you explicitly know are gonna run fast
and that's why you avoid those things
and then you can have tests that you
know are gonna run a little bit slower
and they are gonna hit those things
because that's what you need to do at
some point you need to hit the database
and ensure that you know all you you can
have a bunch of tests that run really
quickly and mock things out and that's
great they give you some confidence but
at the end of the day you want at least
one test I would imagine that hits the
database to ensure that integration is
correct mm-hmm
in your book there's a categorization of
tests you have different kinds of unit
tests can you walk us through some of
them and explain what you what you
address with those categories I'm sure
so I've picked a few so the first one
would be a state verification yep it's
the state verification I'm not sure if
it was first defined in the X unit
patterns book but that's the first time
I ran into it and the definition is you
inspect the state of the system under
test after it has been exercised and
compare it to the expected state so it's
all basically about setting up some
state running a little bit of code and
then verifying the state is as you
expect it mm-hmm that will be like
trying weather
I add something to the system want to
see whether it's there after I've added
it that's the kind of thing yes yes
you're more likely to do say and assert
equals to verify that the value is what
you think it would be the next one's the
behavior verification sure also I
believe defined in next unit patterns
will definitely define there I don't
know if it originated there it's capture
the indirect outputs of the system under
test as they occur and compare them to
the expected behavior so in this case
you're you're doing you're actually
comparing the behavior you're not
necessarily comparing the results of the
behavior so an example would be maybe
checking something out of a library and
instead of looking at the state of the
library and saying that book is there
and then you check it out and then you
look and say that that book is not there
that would be your kind of state-based
classic example instead you mock the
library out and you say well I mean I
guess there's before and after but some
frameworks would allow you to say I'm
expecting someone to take this book from
me and that's your verification other
libraries would just say I'm a mock
library talk to me later and then you
take the book out of the library and
then you say by the way I'd like you to
verify that I took the book out of the
library so that's that's behavior
verification so what do you gain from
categorizing tests this way this is how
to talk about them differently are the
different rules for those different
kinds of tests uh you know in a good in
a bad way I think there are different
rules I'm not sure that there's actually
for me personally there's no winner
there's no better way to test there are
definitely people who prefer behavior
verification and specifically I think
growing object-oriented software
Goo's is a fantastic book that really
focuses on behavior verification but
people have been doing state
verification for years and it's not like
they're failing so at the end of the day
I think you really are best serve to
look at both and see which style fits
you the best
and
then go from there I would say for me
it's always been a mixture of both I I
prefer to do state where possible but
there are definite aspects of behavior
verification such as stubbing out
collaborators that I found far superior
to working with concrete collaborators
so it's it's worth every software
engineers time to get familiar with both
and read all the literature that they
can on both and then make a
determination on what they see is more
successful mm-hmm you had it you have a
category of unit tests which is called
unit tests I was kind of puzzled by that
I think it was just the unit test
umbrella there's there's there a couple
of different definitions within unit
test well so Martin Fowler you know
again convinced me that trying to
redefine unit test would be a terrible
idea so I think that there are two
subcategories of unit tests that are
valuable specifically the the tests that
we talked about a little while earlier
tests that don't access the file system
don't cross any boundary no messaging
framework no database I like to call
those solitary unit tests and solitary
unit tests also focus on testing a
single class at a time so in the example
of libraries and books you know you
could theoretically test not only a
library but also the books in the
library within your library tests but I
would consider that to be more of an
integration test something that you know
integration of the class is something
that I like to call a sociable unit test
so a solitary unit test would focus
exclusively on the library within the
library tests and it would probably rely
on Stub books and a solitary book unit
test would test all of the attributes of
the book and the value the value in this
distinction is at some point you're
going to make a change to the book and
you have to decide how important is it
to you that the book tests fail probably
important and how important is it to you
that the library tests fail whenever the
book changes if you're looking for that
level of integration
and many examples of that level
integration then maybe you're fine
working with social unit tests all the
time but if you would like to be able to
change the book without having to touch
the library tests basically avoiding
cascading failures something that I like
to put a lot of effort into then instead
you can again work with what what I like
to call a solitary unit test which will
stop out the books whenever you're
working with the library basically
isolating you from the changes within
book I think that don't cross boundaries
thing is pretty common I'd be surprised
if people hadn't run into that at some
point and it's basically just a speed
thing you know nobody wants to again I
think nobody would even rely on a unit
test suite that took ten minutes to run
so the the real combo that I like to do
to be honest is let's say that you have
this library example and you want to
check out books and let's say for some
reason the library charges so the
library charges for these books and you
want to verify the cost of checking out
a book so you have book tests and you
verify all of the charges within your
book tests and then the library itself
has an inventory and you also test the
inventory and everything else that's
interesting about the library in library
tests these tests are completely
isolated you know maybe the real library
has some type of connection to a file
system or database and you mock that out
during or excuse me you stub that out
specifically during your library tests
your library solitaire unit tests and
everything runs quickly and everything's
wonderful but like I said before at some
point you want to know that when you go
to check out a book from the library
that book is gonna be out of the
database this is going to be important
and so what I like to do is write as
many solitary unit tests as I possibly
can and then write one or two sociable
unit tests that way I have confidence
that the integration of everything works
but I don't have to test my corner cases
with slow and brittle socialable unit
tests I can test my corner cases with
fast and robust solitary unit tests
mm-hmm
as you mentioned the terms I have to
just briefly ask you to explain the
difference between the stub and a mock
sure sure a mock is used primarily in
behavior based tests or in my opinion
should be used primarily in behavior
based tests and actually used for
verification so in the case of the
library where you want to check out the
book you could create a library mock
check out the book and then ask the mock
if the book had been checked out
successfully and that asking is the key
and the important thing in my opinion
you don't really want to create mocks
and not verify although unfortunately
that's a bit common to do in Java stubs
specifically you don't verify they just
always return can simple responses and
you never really have to worry about
their interactions mm-hmm okay so if you
look you mentioned that before if you if
you look at the code base if you look at
a test code base you sometimes get the
feeling that something's horribly wrong
what are some of those things that you
could that people can improve about that
tests what are some specific things to
look for and change to make the tests
better apart from throwing them away if
they make no sense I think there are a
bunch of small things that you can do to
really help the team out so number one
just get rid of the setup methods well
actually before that get rid of any
loops any loops in the code base they're
probably just going to confuse so split
those up into individual tests then you
can look to get rid of the setup method
because you know you don't open a test
class see a failing test and get some
immediate alert that hey you should go
look in the setup but really that would
that would be helpful right if it told
you you know this isn't the whole story
so I think getting rid of setup and
putting the whole story within the tests
is another valuable thing to do I also
can't stand expected values that are not
literals it bothers me to look at a
failing test and to say alright I have a
failing test and I have a method call
for the expected value and I have a
method call for the actual
and now I have to figure out both to try
to find which is wrong because expected
values can be wrong also mm-hmm so I I
personally prefer to expect literals
sometimes you can't expect a literal in
the case of a money object maybe you
want to expect a money object or really
any value object to be honest you really
have two paths there you can either say
you know perhaps money dot to double and
then use a double as your expected value
and then you're back to expecting
literals and that works well or I think
you could also write custom assertions
and custom assertions are great because
they can also be tested so you have
confidence that they work as expected so
I would say either expect expect
literals or write a custom assertion for
any value object that you're testing but
make those your expected values after
that it starts to get more controversial
and I would say you know people should
try things and then use what they find
valuable
I personally believe in the one
assertion per unit test rule I'm pretty
disappointed when I find multiple
assertions in a test and you know maybe
the first or second assertion fails and
now you're left in the position of - in
my opinion inferior choices you either
fix the first assertion and then
mentally try to decide if the other
assertion is going to the remaining
assertions will pass or fail which is
annoying you shouldn't have to look at
that yourself there's no reason for that
manual effort or you have to run the
tests and then if another one's broken
then you fix that one and then rerun the
tests and continue this loop until
things work so I think it's I think it's
superior to have one assertion per test
after that really the big one that I
recommend to people are just creating
builders object mother was a was a
famous pattern for a little while and
it's very scenario based and it works
very well when you first start using it
but then it starts to break down as you
need more variation on data but nap
price wrote tons of material years ago
on creating test data builders and
there's an upfront cost to creating the
data builders but after you create the
data builders kind of the data builder
framework
if you will then you can very succinctly
create test data within your tests that
allow you to you know without a setup
method quickly instantiate objects and
see how they're interacting and
understand an entire test without having
to navigate to helper methods I talked
about that's a bit about this object
mother pattern because I'm not sure
everybody's familiar with that sure
I think it was you know I don't know
where it was invented but I was first
exposed to it that thought works and it
was pretty simple you know you would
just say I want a customer and there
would be kind of a persona if you will
of customer Bob and customer mary and
customer Joan and Bob would have a
couple attributes and Mary would have a
couple attributes and Joan would have a
couple attributes and they would be
complex
there would be entire object hierarchies
or a graph if you will of the different
attributes and so this person they
belong to this organization and may have
this birthday and may be related to
someone else and you know perhaps one of
these people has two children and
another person has no children and you
have this persona that you use within
your system and that's great
whenever that's what you need maybe you
have four personas that go out through
the entire system and you always use
them and you start to think of them
almost like a teammate you know all I
need to do is write a test for Bob to be
off on Tuesday and my calendar program
and the whole team knows who bob is and
what all Bob's attributes are and that
works out pretty well but then when you
want like you know Bob except he lost
his job or Bob except he no longer has a
car and then you started changing Bob
around and maybe Bob's immutable but if
Bob's not immutable then the order of
test running can have some type of
impact or you have to rely on
reinitializing Bob every time and so
basically once you start sharing Bob
around in multiple tests then you start
to run into problems pretty quickly and
basically as a reaction to these
problems well at least I believe it was
a reaction of these problems people
moved to the more general
test data builders which don't have a
bob or a Joan or Mary they just have a
customer and when you want a customer
over the job you create a customer and
you give that customer the job and by
default the customer doesn't have a job
and that's it you look at a test and you
can see I have a customer
oh and that customer has a job great I
don't have to look at a test and say I
have a bob I don't remember if bob has a
job or not let me look into that okay so
we've talked about individual tests
let's talk a bit about the whole picture
of a set of tests I think we've talked a
bit about it in by mentioning that some
tests are more valuable than others but
if there is something else that that one
can use as a pattern to come up with a
good set of tests something that makes
sense as a whole how do you look at the
big picture
my approach to test Suites in general is
I think there's value and I don't know
most tests that people come up with
these days and it's just a matter of
getting the ratios correct so for me I
like to make everything as solitary as I
can to begin with so any these days I'm
working with Clojure so kind of a
functional language any any function
that has any value and and any corner
cases or any branches within it I guess
I will test that as a solitary unit test
as much as I possibly can so follow all
branches different test data inputs
basically try to test it as much as I
possibly can but in isolation and from
there I want to know that it works
within the system so I'll go to a higher
level maybe the other functions that
rely on the function that we've
solitarily tested and I'll verify that
the integration works so you know maybe
you have a piece of code that has two
inputs and it has two branches and so
you think ten solitary unit tests are
reasonable that's great now you have
confidence on your two branches and your
two types of input you probably only
need one maybe two sociable unit tests
at that point because you've already
covered the behavior of the function
very well so now all you really
to test is the integration of the
function so you're likely to be able to
do that with significantly less tests so
really may be able to get by with one
social unit test at that point just one
social unit test to verify that the
function integrates as you'd expect so I
kind of work with ratios like that make
every single thing that I can a solitary
unit test and cover every single branch
that I possibly can with solitary unit
tests and then at the point where a
branch can't be covered or at the point
where I need to test integration of that
function or method then I write a social
unit test and I write only as many as I
need to verify the integration that
works pretty well and then after that I
do believe in the value of higher level
tests also which live under so many
different names but I don't know I guess
we could call them integration tests you
know a high level test that will bring
up an entire component of the system so
those are valuable and trying to
remember somebody came up with the test
pyramid I can't remember off the top of
my head but Martin Fowler pointed me at
that also and that seems like a very
reasonable approach so at the bottom you
have a very wide base of the pyramid and
that's where all of your solitary unit
tests go and then in the middle you have
your sociable unit tests which help you
verify that everything is collaborating
in the way that you'd expect and at the
very top you have your highest level
tests your high level tests that verify
that the system maybe from its inputs
and outputs
is working as you expect so maybe you
find a way to send a message through an
actual messaging system into a running
process and then you look in the
database so you look in the file system
to see that the system reacted in the
way you'd expect so I believe there's
value in those as well I don't call
those unit tests but I do call them
I guess high level tests most of the
time and I think those are great that's
a great compliment to your unit tests as
long as you can keep them under about a
dozen once you get past a dozen I think
they become a little bit unmaintainable
so I guess you can maybe extrapolate
some numbers from there maybe a dozen
high level tests
and then I don't know maybe a hundred or
200 sociable tests and then from there
you know it's gonna depend on the
codebase obviously the size of the
codebase but it seems hard to believe
that you would need more than 2,000
solitary unit tests because I don't know
it just seems hard to believe that any
system has that many functions that are
critical absolutely critical to its
functioning correctly so what do you
think is a reasonable relation a
reasonable fraction of the time that
developers should spend on writing tests
versus writing production code is it
does it make sense to ask the question
or is it stupid since it's a new
question for me I don't know I've never
really thought about it I mean in some
ways you would say that maybe 5050 would
be reasonable in some ways you would say
that if you write the tests and then you
implement the simplest thing that could
possibly work and then you readjust to
make sure that it was gonna be good for
maintenance then perhaps you'd spend
more time on testing I would say you
have to balance that with well I don't
test every single thing because some
things are not as important as others so
I I would say that I probably spend 40%
of my time testing and that's that's a
combination of unit testing high level
testing and manual testing I think I
think that's a pretty reasonable
percentage anything between 30 and 50
percent I think would be reasonable if
you're over 50% maybe you're doing
something wrong I mean if you're if
you're over 50% because you're doing TDD
and then as soon as you're done
implementing features you're deleting
those tests then maybe you're fine but
if you're spending more than 50% of your
time in the tests because you have
brittle and unmaintainable tests then I
think something's wrong you mentioned if
you're doing development and closure
these days just as a more general kind
of question related to that how does
unit testing change when you use a
different programming language or it
doesn't change at all
uh you know I was trying to think of a
good example of what I do differently
right after I mentioned Clojure I
thought how does this really apply based
on um based on my java history and I
don't know that there's really any
difference I mean to me you know I've
given such general things that are
important to me when it comes to testing
it doesn't really matter what language
I'm working in a test is either testing
a feature that is important and
therefore needs to stick around and
needs to be readable or it's not and it
doesn't matter if that's state based or
behavior based or enclosure or in Java
they're just kind of higher-level rules
that I think go beyond language and
domain and approach at the end of the
day you really want to stick with tests
that are valuable and and tests that are
maintainable for the team some things I
guess could be different you know you
would think that testing is procedural
and setup is a template method pattern
from object-oriented software and so
maybe we would get away from that in a
functional language but it turns out the
people who have been working with unit
tests are so comfortable with their
styles of testing that it doesn't matter
which language you jump between the vast
majority of the X unit test unit
whatever unit prefix anything unit
frameworks they all are extremely
similar some frameworks that are
starting to diverge and it gives you a
different approach to testing for
example like the the checking the quick
check and the quick check derivatives
those are different but I don't know
that it would be fair to say that those
are unit tests I think that's kind of a
different style that maybe will evolve
on its own or maybe will get rolled back
in but it's still early days and all the
existing testing frameworks are just for
better or worse they're very similar so
I find my style to kind of transfer
between languages fair enough okay so is
there anything else you'd like to add
did we miss anything did should I have
asked you something that we didn't talk
about
I guess I'm the only thing I would add
is that I hope more people find this
stuff interesting I hope more people
instead of giving up on tests they look
for ways to increase the value the ROI
on the tests that they are writing and I
I mean practitioners and I also mean the
people who are out the experts if you
will that are out in the world I think
Kevin honey presents fantastic stuff on
testing I think his style is different
than mine and that's okay I think he
still has a lot of value to add I think
Michael feathers has a lot of value to
add Brian Merrick has been really
focused on the testing space for so long
and he has a lot of value to add but we
don't have a lot of mature documentation
so I think I think people that are
looking to get more return on investment
are gonna have to stick with blog posts
and with presentations recorded
presentations at this point and that's
really the best we have and that's fine
and and we should be looking out for
each other and pointing those out
whenever they come up you know unit
testing is a little boring if you will
these days but isn't it interesting that
something that we find so much value in
and is so old and we consider boring is
still being thrown out by people that we
respect I mean there's some type of
mismatch there and so hopefully more
people will write more stuff on this but
I don't think we're there yet
unfortunately and I hope I hope people
do try to find their own ways to be more
effective and I hope they write about
those also and I I think other authors
should get involved and start writing
about their own styles of testing good
so thank you very much for talking to me
today Jay and thanks to Elizabeth for
listening thank you very much
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio now to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on Twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
you